Guide to the Agnes E. Meyer Collection of Paul Claudel
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Agnes E. Meyer collection of Paul Claudel
1897-1957
GEN MSS 456
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.42
(4 boxes) + 1 portfolio
Chiefly ALS written by Claudel to Meyer and writings by Claudel, including a holograph of the second version of his play La ville, poems, and religious writings. Also present are two photographs of Claudel, a small amount of letters to Meyer from other correspondents, printed material, and clippings. Letters from Claudel concern his friendship with Meyer, their discussions about religion and Claudel's ardent Catholicism, and his writing and travels. Many letters discuss Catholic doctrine and Claudel's beliefs at length, urging Meyer's conversion to Catholicism and addressing her questions about religion, including five letters later published in his Positions et propositions (1934). Letters also discuss production of his dramatic works, collaboration with Darius Milhaud and Arthur Honegger, his views on the United States, his experiences in France during the Second World War, and family news. Other correspondence includes single letters from Milhaud and from Paul Petit, a few letters from Claudel's daughter Reine Claudel and his illegitimate daughter Louise Vetch, and a letter and printed pamphlet from L. Droüart de Lézey, concerning the Léproserie de Kōyama, Japan. Also present are holograph notes regarding La ville and holograph poems written for Meyer; additional poems are enclosed with Claudel's letters.
Meyer, Agnes E., 1887-1970
Claudel, Paul, 1868-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Agnes E. Meyer and her children, ca. 1960-1972.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Portfolio, folder 43 :Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
AGNES ELIZABETH ERNST MEYER (1887-1970) AND PAUL CLAUDEL (1868-1955)
Agnes Elizabeth Ernst, journalist, author, and lecturer, was born in New York City. In 1910 she married Eugene Meyer, a financier who purchased The Washington Post in 1933. The Meyers lived in Mount Kisco, New York, and Washington, D.C., where Agnes Meyer was active in government service and social reform.
Meyer met the French writer and diplomat Paul Claudel in Washington, D.C., early in his term as ambassador to the United States, 1927-1933. They began a friendship and correspondence which continued after Claudel's return to Europe in 1933 and lasted until his death in 1955. Meyer discussed her relationship with Claudel in her autobiography Out of These Roots (Boston: Little, Brown, 1953).
Scope and Contents
The Agnes E. Meyer Collection of Paul Claudel consists of correspondence, writings by Claudel, and a small amount of printed material, clippings, and photographs. The collection documents Claudel's friendship with Meyer, their discussions about religion and Claudel's ardent Catholicism, and Meyer's interest in his philosophy and writing.
The collection is housed in two boxes, two oversize boxes, and one portfolio and is organized into three series: Letters to Agnes E. Meyer, Writings by Paul Claudel, and Other Papers. The portfolio contains Restricted Fragile materials.
Series I, Letters to Agnes E. Meyer, consists of two subseries, each arranged chronologically: Letters From Paul Claudel and Letters From Other Correspondents. Letters from Claudel concern his friendship with Meyer, his religious thought, and his writing and travels. Most letters were written in 1929-1933, with a concentration during 1929-1930, when Claudel wrote frequent letters urging Meyer's conversion to Catholicism and addressing her questions about religion. Many of these letters discuss Catholic doctrine and Claudel's beliefs at length, including five letters, 1929 Dec-1930 Apr, which were published by Claudel as "Cinq lettres à Madame A. E. M." in his Positions et propositions (1934). Claudel also discusses production of his Christophe Colomb, The Satin Slipper, Jeanne d'Arc au bûcher, and other dramatic works, collaboration with Darius Milhaud and Arthur Honegger, and other literary matters. Some letters include holograph poems written by Claudel for Meyer, of which many were written in honor of the feast day of Saint Agnes. Other enclosures include a typescript of a speech given by Claudel at the opening of the Rodin Museum, Philadelphia, 1929, and part of a proof of The Satin Slipper, with holograph corrections, 1931. Letters also discuss Claudel's views of the United States, his experiences in France during the Second World War, and family news, particularly regarding Meyer's and Claudel's children. A few letters are accompanied by notes written by Meyer regarding their contents or by typed transcripts. Also present is a copy of a single letter from Meyer to Claudel, carbon typescript, 1939.
Letters From Other Correspondents includes a few letters from Claudel's daughter Reine Claudel and from his illegitimate daughter Louise Vetch, discussing her relationship with Claudel and her mother Rose Vetch, a single letter from Darius Milhaud concerning the production of Christophe Colomb, and a single letter from Paul Petit. Also present is a letter from L. Droüart de Lézey, a missionary to leprosy patients in Japan, enclosing a printed pamphlet about the Léproserie de Koyama, to which Claudel and Meyer gave support.
Series II, Writings by Paul Claudel, includes a holograph of the second version of his play La ville, [1897-1900], bound in a volume and accompanied by holograph notes written for Meyer about the play. The volume also contains several holograph poems. Also present in this series are additional holograph poems written for Meyer and a few published and manuscript writings on religious subjects. Other poems and religious writings are present in Claudel's letters.
Series III, Other Papers, consists of a printed pamphlet containing a speech made by Claudel at Georgetown University, with holograph corrections; two photographs of Claudel; clippings relating to him; a copy of an essay written by G. K. Chesterton, typescript; and a printed pamphlet containing a lecture given by Chesterton at College of the Holy Cross, Worcester, Massachusetts.
Authors, French -- 20th Century -- Correspondence; Missions to leprosy patients -- Japan; Photographic prints; Claudel, Paul, 1868-1955 -- Religion; Claudel, Paul, 1868-1955; Claudel, Paul, 1868-1955 ( Positions et propositions); Claudel, Paul, 1868-1955 ( Ville); Claudel, Reine; Honegger, Arthur, 1892-1955; Lézey, L. Droüart de; Meyer, Agnes E., 1887-1970; Milhaud, Darius, 1892-1974; Petit, Paul, 1914-1981; Vetch, Louise; Catholic Church ( Apologetic works); Léproserie de Kōhama
- Letters to Agnes E. Meyer, 1928-1954; Series I; 0.63; (1.5 boxes)
  - LETTERS FROM PAUL CLAUDEL
    - Letters, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1929 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 1929 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 1929 Jul (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters, 1929 Aug (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes an enclosed letter from an unidentified correspondent, possibly to AEM
    - Letters, 1929 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters, 1929 Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters, 1930 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters, 1930 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters, 1930 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes an enclosed letter from Louise Vetch to PC
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Oversize, box 4, folder 48
    - Letters, 1930 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes an enclosed wood carving of a cross
    - Letters, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes postcards showing PC and patients of the Léproserie de Koyama, Japan
    - Letters, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letters, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes an enclosed note from Sir Winston Churchill to AEM
    - Letters, [1928-33?] (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - Letters, 1934-36 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Letters, 1937-39 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Letters, 1940-42 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Letters, 1944-49 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      See also: Oversize, Box 4, folder 49
    - Letters, 1950-54 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Includes an enclosed photograph of a drawing of PC in an unidentified hand
    - Letters, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - LETTERS FROM OTHER CORRESPONDENTS
    - Claudel, Reine, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Droüart de Lézey, L., 1929 Jan 23 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      With Koyama Leper Hospital (1928), printed pamphlet
    - Meyer, Ruth, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Milhaud, Darius, 1930 Sep 11 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Petit, Paul, 1929 Sep 10 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Vetch, Louise, 1950-51 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - ----, [René?], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Writings by Paul Claudel, 1897-1950; Series II; 0.1; (.25 box)
  - "A Madame A. E. M.," poem, holograph, signed, 1931 Dec 25
  - "A Madame A. E. Meyer," poem, holograph, signed, 1932 Dec 24 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "After Chinese Patterns," poems, holograph, signed, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    With a typed transcript
  - Deux apôtres...Image saintes de Bohême ([Paris]: Rivière), no. 43 of an edition of 150, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "Farewell!," poem, holograph, signed, 1937 Jun 11 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Inscription to AEM, holograph, signed, 1950 Nov 20
  - Le jardin aride: parabole (Paris: [Nouvelle revue francaise]), 1934 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Non impedias musicam (S.l.: Éditions du Cerf), offprint, inscribed to AEM, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Sainte Agnès," poem, holograph, 1932 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - "Sainte Agnès," poem, holograph, 1938 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "The Speech-Tree Ballad," poem, holograph, signed, 1929 Sep 11 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "La ville," play, second version, holograph, in bound volume, with notes written for AEM, [1897-1900]
  - "Le voleur volé," typescript, 1928 Nov (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Les XV mystères du rosaire," holograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    With brief holograph notes
- Other Papers, 1930-1957; Series III; 0.1; (.25 box)
  - Chesterton, G. K. "'The Twelve Men' from Tremendous Trifles," typed transcript (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Chestertoniana: Mr. Chesterton at Holy Cross (Worcester, Mass.), no. 110 of an edition of 200, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Clippings, 1930-57, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Le Figaro littéraire. "Numéro spécial sur Paul Claudel", 1955 Mar 5
  - Georgetown University. Founders Day, printed pamphlet containing a speech by Claudel, with holograph corrections, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Two reproductions of a photograph of PC made by Edward Steichen and inscribed to AM (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Photograph of PC made by Yeghi Art Studio, mounted print, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Oversize, 2.59; (2 boxes)
  - "La ville," second version (in Series II), [1897-1900] (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Letter from PC to AEM (in Series I), 1930 Jul 14 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Letter from PC to AEM (in Series I), 1946 Sep 20 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - "A Madame A. E. M." (in Series II), 1931 Dec 25 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Inscription to AEM (in Series II), 1950 Nov 20 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Le Figaro littéraire. "Numéro spécial sur Paul Claudel" (in Series III), 1955 Mar 5 (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Restricted Fragile
  (1 portfolio)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 2 Portfolio folder 43: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 43 (Box Port, folder 53)